Mss.Rec.72 Mss.Rec.72
American Philosophical Society
Linguistic data in the Sandia dialect of Tiwa
1969-1970
Mss.Rec.72
American Philosophical Society
29.0 Reel(s)
Includes vocabulary; texts; analysis of the Sandia material by an Isleta informant; household items; foods; directions; natural phenomena; buildings; fruits; time expressions; verbs; adverbs; checking George L. Trager's material; pronominal reference; greetings; animal names (including domesticated); festivals; other ethnographic information. Tape 1 includes Tewa (not Tiwa) texts, vocabulary, speech, and song recorded by Ernest Riechert of Wycliffe Bible Translators at Nambe Pueblo, New Mexico.
29 sound tape reels (25 hr., 4 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, 2 track, mono; 7 in.
Brandt, Elizabeth A.
Riechert, Ernest
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presented by Elizabeth Anne Brandt in 1970. This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Isleta dialect; Sandia dialect; Sound recordings; Tewa language; Tiwa language
- Audio recordings
  - Speech from two Tewa speakers, 1968; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:41; Brandt, Elizabeth A.; Riechert, Ernest
    Scope and Contents note
    Copied on to reel-to-reel tape by Ernest Riechert, Wycliffe Bible Translators. Original recording was made on a cassette recorder.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Audiocassette) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Anthropological linguistics; Nambe Pueblo (N.M.); Tewa language
  - Tewa speech and song, 1968; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:33; Brandt, Elizabeth A.; Montoya, Ilimiliano; Riechert, Ernest
    Anthropological linguistics; Nambe Pueblo (N.M.); Tewa Indians--Music; Tewa language
  - Phonetics - texts & keywords [1 of 2], 1968-07-10; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:25:18; Brandt, Elizabeth A.; Riechert, Ernest
  - Phonetics - texts & keywords [2 of 2], 1968-07-20; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:35; Brandt, Elizabeth A.; Riechert, Ernest
  - General Tiwa vocabulary [1 of 2], 1968-07-25; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:22; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Primarily comprises a discussion of kinship terms and names of positions in local government.
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Kinship; Tiwa Indians--Politics and government; Tiwa language
  - General Tiwa vocabulary [2 of 2], 1968-07-25; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:40; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Entirely in English. Primarily concerns recent happenings at the pueblo.
    Anthropological linguistics; Mourning customs--United States--New Mexico; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa dance; Tiwa Indians--Social life and customs
  - Analysis of Sandia material by an Isleta informant [1 of 3], 1969-08-25; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:59; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Isleta dialect; Isleta Pueblo (N.M.); Sandia dialect; Tiwa language
  - Analysis of Sandia material by an Isleta informant [2 of 3], 1969-08-25; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:02; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
  - Analysis and comparison of Sandia material by an Isleta informant [2 of 3], 1969-10-14; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:27; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
  - Analysis and comparison of Sandia material by an Isleta informant [3 of 3], 1969-10-14; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:27:04; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Isleta dialect; Isleta Pueblo (N.M.); Kivas--New Mexico; Sandia dialect; Tiwa Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Tiwa language
  - Items in the household [1 of 2], 1969-07-11; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:13; Brandt, Elizabeth A.; Sevedra, Mary
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Material culture; Tiwa language
  - Items in the household [2 of 2], 1969-07-11; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:16; Brandt, Elizabeth A.; Sevedra, Mary
  - Analysis of Sandia material by an Isleta informant [3 of 3], 1969-08-25; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:50; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Predominantly in English, concerning anthropological information. Linguistic analysis begins at 26:55. Original tape has no side 2.
    Isleta dialect; Isleta Pueblo (N.M.); Sandia dialect; Tiwa Indians--Religion; Tiwa Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Tiwa language
  - Conversations & texts -- 2 informants, 1969-07-17; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:25:05; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    There is some intermittent sound distortion on the recording due to the microphone being too close to one of the speakers.
    Anthropological linguistics; Leatherwork; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Social life and customs; Tiwa language
  - General Vocabulary [1 of 2], 1968-07-25; 08-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:40; Brandt, Elizabeth A.; Sevedra, Mary
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language
  - General Vocabulary [2 of 2], 1968-07-25; 08-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:47; Brandt, Elizabeth A.; Sevedra, Mary
  - Elicitation of terms for food, 1969-07-10; 09-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:50; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Program contains a consistent hum from the original recording equipment and runs slow at moments.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Food; Tiwa language
  - Elicitation of terms for directions, 1969-07-10; 09-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:44; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Program runs slightly fast.
    Anthropological linguistics; Cardinal points; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language
  - Analysis and comparison of Sandia material by an Isleta informant [1 of 3], 1969-10-14; 10-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:48; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Side 1 of this tape has not yet been digitized.
  - Elicitation and discussion of terms for directions [1 of 2], 1969-07-01; 11-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:48; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Cardinal points; Isleta dialect; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language
  - Elicitation and discussion of terms for directions [2 of 2], 1969-07-01; 11-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:55; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    In English only. Discussion mainly of language acquisition of English and Tiwa.
    Anthropological linguistics; English language--Acquisition; Kivas; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Education; Tourists
  - General vocabulary, with ethnographic information [1 of 2], 1968-08-21; 12-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:31; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Social life and customs; Tiwa language
  - General vocabulary, with ethnographic information [2 of 2], 1968-08-21; 12-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:29; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
  - "How do you say ___?", verb forms, expressions of time, 1968-08-08; 13-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:14; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language; Tiwa language--Verbs
  - Pronomial reference, verb forms, 1968-08-08; 13-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:54; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Time--Terminology; Tiwa language; Tiwa language--Pronouns; Tiwa language--Verbs
  - Vocabulary from G.L. Trager's 1930s word list, some verb forms, 1968-08-07; 14-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:20; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language--Glossaries, vocabularies, etc.; Tiwa language--Verbs
  - Verb forms, present, past, future, 1968-08-07; 14-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:47; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
  - Verbs and Adverbs, 1969-07-15; 15-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:54; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language; Tiwa language--Adverbs; Tiwa language--Number; Tiwa language--Verbs
  - General texts, work with new informant, 1969-07-17; 15-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:52; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language; Tiwa language--Grammar
  - Elicitation to check vocabulary from G.L. Trager's word list [1 of 2], 1968-08-23; 16-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:27; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
  - Elicitation to check vocabulary from G.L. Trager's word list [2 of 2], 1968-08-23; 16-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:35; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
  - Recording of G.L. Trager's Sandia File - check T, T´, T`, U, U, W, Y, nos. 299-386 [1 of 2], 1968-08-09; 17-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:39; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Cardinal points; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language; Tiwa language--Phonetics
  - Recording of G.L. Trager's Sandia File - check T, T´, T`, U, U, W, Y, nos. 299-386 [2 of 2], 1968-08-09; 17-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:57; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language; Tiwa language--Phonetics
  - Short texts, pronomial reference, some greetings, 1969-10-21; 18-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:44; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language; Tiwa language--Pronouns
  - Kinship, some verb forms, 1969-10-22; 18-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:25:42; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Kinship; Tiwa language; Tiwa language--Verbs
  - Elicitation of terms for directions [1 of 2], 1969-10-23; 19-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:37; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Cardinal points; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians; Tiwa language
  - Elicitation of terms for directions [2 of 2], 1969-10-23; 19-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:29:19; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
  - Sandia texts [1 of 2], 1969-10-24; 20-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:29:37; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Sentences given by consultant in the Sandia dialect of Tiwa and in English, with discussion and some elicitation from researcher.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language; Zia Pueblo (N.M.)
  - Sandia texts [2 of 2], 1969-10-24; 20-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:27:29; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
  - Elicitation of terms for natural phenomena, 1969-10-24; 21-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:46; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language; Weather
  - Elicitation of names of domestic animals [1 of 2], 1969-10-27; 22-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:13; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Includes terms for horses, cattle, and pigs.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Spanish language--Influence on Tiwa; Tiwa Indians--Domestic animals; Tiwa language
  - Elicitation of names of domestic animals [2 of 2], 1969-10-27; 22-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:02; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Includes terms for pigs, sheep, goats, chickens, ducks, turkeys, geese, pigeons, doves.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Domestic animals; Tiwa language
  - Elicitation of names of domestic and game animals, 1969-10-27; 23-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:01; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
  - Elicitation of names of game animals and discussion of Sandia government and ceremony, 1969-10-27; 23-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:09; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Domestic animals; Tiwa Indians--Politics and government; Tiwa Indians--Social life and customs; Tiwa language
  - Elicitation of names of animals [1 of 4], 1969-10-28; 24-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:10; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Elk; Leatherwork; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language
  - Elicitation of names of animals [2 of 4], 1969-10-28; 24-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:27; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Bows and arrows; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Material culture; Tiwa language
  - Elicitation of names of animals [3 of 4], 1969-10-28; 25-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:12; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Bees; Birds; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language
  - Elicitation of names of animals [4 of 4], 1969-10-28; 25-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:03; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Lizards; Rattlesnakes; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language
  - Elicitation of terms for natural phenomena, adobe, buildings, and fruits, 1969-07-14; 26-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:24; Brandt, Elizabeth A.; Sevedra, Mary
    Fruits; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa architecture; Tiwa language; Weather
  - Elicitation of verb forms and greetings, 1969-07-15; 26-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:14; Brandt, Elizabeth A.; Sevedra, Mary
    Anthropological linguistics; Salutations; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language; Tiwa language--Verbs
  - Discussion and elicitation of animal names [1 of 2], 1969-10-29; 27-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:03; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Animals--New Mexico; Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language
  - Discussion and elicitation of animal names [2 of 2], 1969-10-29; 27-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:05; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Animals--New Mexico; Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa language; Trees--New Mexico
  - Verb forms, Speaker Group III or IV [1 of 2], 1970-01-12; 28-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:44; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
  - Verb forms, Speaker Group III or IV [2 of 2], 1970-01-12; 28-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:46; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Politics and government; Tiwa language; Tiwa language--Verbs
  - Governing terms & ethnographic information on governing, 1970-01-12; 29-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:16; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Predominantly in English, with some Tiwa terminology. Program contains corrupted digital sound quality from RDAT transfer, from 7:34 to 7:55. At 7:46, a three-second silent gap has been left to reflect 20 seconds of signal silence that have been removed at that point.
    Anthropological linguistics; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Politics and government; Tiwa language
  - Discussion of relative & relatedness, adapation, longevity of Indians, 1970-01-12; 29-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:49; Brandt, Elizabeth A.
    Anthropological linguistics; Longevity; Sandia dialect; Sandia Pueblo (N.M.); Tiwa Indians--Kinship; Tiwa language